

Todd M. Ellis

DATA ANALYST & STATISTICAL PROGRAMMER

Greater Hobart Region, Tasmania, Australia April 2023

□+61 466 683 552 | ☑ toddellis.wa@gmail.com | ☑ 0000-0002-4410-8676 | ☑ q6vTAroAAAAJ | ☑ Todd-Ellis-4 |

otoddellis | in tmichaelellis

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY.

I'm a data analyst and scientist with a background in forest ecology, physical geography, and higher education. I've worked as an analyst in a wide variety of laboratory, field, and office settings across the United States and Australia. Over the course of my career, I've developed novel mathematical tools and statistical models; maintained relational databases and statistical packages used for conducting data analysis and producing standardized reports; trained countless staff, students, and volunteers; and managed complex and critical projects. My research has been published in high-impact, peer-reviewed journals, and I'm also skilled at conveying complex data and information to both casual and experienced stakeholders.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy, Biological Sciences

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania

2019 - present

- · Dissertation: Dynamic mapping and analysis of New South Wales fire regimes: Past, present, and future
- Supervisors: Drs. Grant J. Williamson and David M.J.S. Bowman

Master of Science, Geography

Bellingham, WA, USA

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

2013 - 2016

- Thesis: Climatic drivers of western spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands
- · Supervisor: Dr. Aquila Flower

Bachelor of Science, Physical Geography / Geology

San Marcos, TX, USA

TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY

2007 - 2012

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Data Insights Analyst

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia
2023-01 - present

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (full-time)

- Developing novel student admissions tools and processes using novel data and modelling
- · Leading development and modelling on higher education programs actively improving equity of access for potential applicants
- Providing insights and consulting to university stakeholders across the institution

Adjunct Researcher Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: College of Sciences and Engineering (full-time)

2019-09 - 2023-03

- · Developed complex data-processing and analysis pipelines using high-performance computing and big data
- · Oversaw multi-year projet design and implementation addressing wildfire and global climate change challenges
- Managed custom platform for interactive web-mapping, on-the-fly statistical analyses, and novel data visualisation
- · Collaborated with national and international research teams tackling climate change risk and mitigation

Data Analyst Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (part-time / full-time)

2021-02 - 2023-01

2019-10 - 2021-02

- Developed statistical models and tools for meeting target university milestones
- Managed design and implementation of broad-scale university ML models for directing future university marketing, funding, and course creation
- Designed and implemented programming and data analytics training seminars for institution staff
- Oversaw development of internal reporting and statistical packages

Sustainability Analyst Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (casual)

Processed, analysed, and reported data to promote and review institution programmes

- Developed pipelines for automating data cleaning and collation
- Prepared data and briefings for global institution rankings
- · Promoted nation-wide sustainability targets using data dashboards and reports

Data & GIS Analyst Austin, TX, USA

APEX SYSTEMS: APPLE, INC. (CONTRACT)

· Developed and standardised data-processing methods for vector and multispectral raster datasets

- · Managed and processed corporate GIS databases using data-driven software and programming languages
- · Prepared statistical summaries, models, and analytical reports
- · Led research and development projects to define novel methodologies for geospatial data

Faculty Research Assistant

Wenatchee, WA, USA

2017-11 - 2018-06

2018-12 - 2019-05

OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY: USDA FOREST SERVICE FORESTRY SCIENCES LABORATORY (CONTRACT)

- · Converted complex data and findings into academic and government reports
- · Developed explanatory models for sustainable forest management under climate change
- Created and maintained relational databases for government research
- Gathered and analysed ecological data using statistical software

CONSULTING

2020-08 Predicting fire behaviour using historical satellite imagery

Frontier Development Lab

2019-06 Post-fire logging effects on reburn severity

USDA Forest Service

2018-08 Restoration treatment effects on ponderosa pine growth sensitivity to climate

USDA Forest Service

HONOURS

2022-11 Future Students Staff Excellence 2022 Sustainability Award

University of Tasmania

2021-10 NSW Environment, Energy and Science (DPIE) Eureka Prize for Applied Environmental Research

Australian Museum

2021-09 Future Students Staff Excellence 2021 Sustainability Award

University of Tasmania

2021-08 Certifi-Cat of Appreciation

Ten Lives Cat Centre

2019-09 Tasmania Graduate Research Scholarship (3.5x)

NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub

2019-09 NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Top-Up (3.5x)

NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub

2018-06 Best Fish and Wildlife Science

Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

Foster Parent Hobart, TAS, Australia

TEN LIVES CAT CENTRE

2020-05 - present

Animal Handler
Humane Society of the New Braunfels Area

New Braunfels, TX, USA

Animal Handler

2018-08 - 2019-01

WENATCHEE VALLEY HUMANE SOCIETY

Wenatchee, WA, USA

Technology Tutor

2018-03 - 2018-08

NORTH CENTRAL REGIONAL LIBRARY

Wenatchee, WA, USA

2018-01 - 2018-08